ערב טוב Erev tov we're going to do today ט"ו עמוד ב'
tet-vav amud bet maybe get up to ט"ז. tet-zayin. We pick up
at the very bottom of ט"ו עמוד א'. tet-vav amud aleph. תנן
התם. tnan hatam. Now we ran through a little bit the end
of the עמוד א' amud aleph this morning but but you will
see the גמרא Gemara next tomorrow will be an almost complete repeat
of it. So let's take a look. It says the
following. Alright so our משנה Mishnah had said that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda said there's a debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about whether what happens if you can't hear what
you're saying. That רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says you're not יצא yotzei
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that you are יצא. yotzei. And
the גמרא's Gemara question is whether רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is לכתחילה
l'chatchila would demand that you be able to hear what you're saying
and went back and forth on that in the end it found
that there are both opinions out there. That even לכתחילה l'chatchila you
don't have to hear what you're saying or maybe לכתחילה l'chatchila you
do בדיעבד b'di'avad you don't. And one of those positions is רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the other is a different תנא. tanna. And
now we will continue with that. Let's take a look. תנן התם.
tnan hatam. We taught over there. הכל כשרין לקרות את המגילה חוץ
מחרש שוטה וקטן. hakol k'sherim likrot et hamigilla chutz me'cheresh shoteh v'katan.
Everybody is kosher to read the מגילה Megillah except for חרש cheresh
שוטה shoteh and קטן. katan. A deaf-mute a somebody who is not
of right mind and a minor. רבי יהודה מכשיר בקטן. Rabbi Yehuda
machshir b'katan. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says a קטן katan can read
the מגילה Megillah presumably since it's a rabbinic מצוה mitzvah he allows
a קטן katan to do it. So the גמרא Gemara says מאן
תנא חרש בדיעבד נמי לא? man tanna cheresh b'di'avad nami lo? So
who is the one that says that a חרש cheresh cannot do
it? Here the גמרא Gemara bizarrely thinks that the חרש cheresh means
mute
but not deaf. Normally חרש cheresh of course means deaf-mute but here
the גמרא Gemara thinks that it means mute and thinks that the
only problem here is that you can't hear what you are saying.
You're not משמיע לאזנו. mashmi'a l'ozno. Obviously it's audible other people hear
it but you can't hear it and it's saying here that that
person is not kosher to read the מגילה. Megillah. So who is
the one that says that that's true? אמר רב מתנא Amar Rav
Matna רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. So if חרש cheresh just means that
you can't hear excuse me I said mute I did not mean
mute I meant deaf I'm sorry I don't know what I'm thinking.
So the גמרא Gemara thinks that חרש cheresh here means deaf but
not deaf-mute. So the problem is is that you can't hear what
you are saying okay which is quite funny because חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh v'katan normally always means people that are not halakhically considered
to be a adult or of right mind and so on. But
here the גמרא Gemara is reading חרש cheresh as somebody that's deaf
and the problem is that he can't hear what he's saying. So
who says that that's a problem? רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose it's רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yose. Didn't we taught in the משנה Mishnah הקורא את
שמע ולא השמיע לאזנו יצא. hakorei et Shema v'lo hishmi'a l'ozno yatsa.
If you read the שמע Shema and did not hear what you
were saying you יצא yatsa דברי רבי יהודה divrei Rabbi Yehuda that's
what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי יוסי אומר לא יצא Rabbi
Yose omer lo yatsa you're not יצא. yatsa. So here if חרש
cheresh doesn't work and חרש cheresh just means deaf it has to
be רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that says if you cannot hear what
you're saying you do not fulfill your obligation. So now the גמרא
Gemara continues to say the following. It says ממאי דרבי יוסי היא
בדיעבד נמי לא? mi'mai d'Rabbi Yose hi b'di'avad nami lo? What makes
you think this is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and the point of
this משנה Mishnah of מגילה Megillah is that you're not יצא yatsa
even after the fact? דילמא רבי יהודה היא dilma Rabbi Yehuda hi
maybe the משנה Mishnah that a חרש cheresh person should not read
the מגילה Megillah is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda ולכתחילה הוא דלא u'l'chatchila
hu d'lo and when it says don't read the מגילה Megillah it
means לכתחילה l'chatchila he shouldn't read the מגילה Megillah but בדיעבד b'di'avad
it's okay. אהא בדיעבד שפיר דמי aha b'di'avad shapir dami it would
be okay בדיעבד. b'di'avad. גמרא Gemara says לא סלקא דעתך lo salka
daitach that doesn't make sense that we're only talking about a לכתחילה
l'chatchila problem דקתני חרש דומיא דשוטה וקטן d'ktanei cheresh dumiya d'shoteh v'katan
because it has a list חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh and katan.
מה שוטה וקטן בדיעבד נמי לא mah shoteh v'katan b'di'avad nami lo
the same way שוטה shoteh and קטן katan a person not of
right mind and a minor we know that there you don't fulfill
the obligation even post-facto
אף חרש בדיעבד נמי לא af cheresh b'di'avad nami lo so חרש
cheresh clearly also has to be that even בדיעבד b'di'avad you do
not fulfill your obligation. And again assuming חרש cheresh means just deaf
and not deaf-mute it only makes sense according to רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose that says if you cannot hear what you're saying you do
not fulfill your obligation. So now the גמרא Gemara continues to say
the following. It says ודילמא הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא. v'dilma ha k'itah
v'ha k'itah. No I'm not convinced says the גמרא Gemara maybe some
of these people are not good לכתחילה l'chatchila and some of them
are not good even בדיעבד b'di'avad and maybe חרש cheresh means deaf
and it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and it just means that you
cannot do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. So the גמרא Gemara
says ומי מצית לאוקמה כרבי יהודה? u'mi matsait l'okmah k'Rabbi Yehuda? Now
we're turning back to what was the end of the discussion this
morning. What is רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position? Is רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda position that even לכתחילה l'chatchila you can do it or does
he say that at the outset לכתחילה l'chatchila you can't and it's
only good after the fact? So here we're trying to argue this
משנה Mishnah about מגילה Megillah might be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
might be saying that a חרש cheresh person לכתחילה l'chatchila should not
read the מגילה Megillah and then this becomes our question. Is רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying it's a לכתחילה l'chatchila problem or בדיעבד b'di'avad
problem? So let's take a look. ומי מצית לאוקמה כרבי יהודה הא
מדקתני סיפא רבי יהודה מכשיר בקטן? u'mi matsait l'okmah k'Rabbi Yehuda ha
mid'ktanei seifa Rabbi Yehuda machshir b'katan? How can you say that this
is רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Since the סיפא seifa says רבי יהודה
מכשיר בקטן Rabbi Yehuda machshir b'katan מכלל דרישא לאו רבי יהודה היא.
m'chlal d'reisha lav Rabbi Yehuda hi.
Presumably the רישא reisha is not רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda גמרא Gemara
says ודילמא כולה. v'dilma kula. Maybe it's all רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda.
and תרי גווני קטן Trei gavnei katan and maybe there are two
categories of קטן. katan. חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, Chisora mechasra v'hachi katani,
it's missing some words and here's what it really means to say:
הכל כשרין לקרות את המגילה חוץ מחרש שוטה וקטן. Hakol k'sherim likros
et ha'megillah chutz me'chersh shoteh v'katan.
Anybody can read the מגילה Megillah except חרש שוטה וקטן. chersh shoteh
v'katan. במה דברים אמורים, Ba'meh devarim amurim, what type of a קטן
katan cannot read it? בקטן שלא הגיע לחינוך, B'katan she'lo higia l'chinuch,
if he's so young he's under the age of חינוך. chinuch. Pretty
amazing that he's under the age of חינוך chinuch and he's still
reading the מגילה. Megillah. Okay, but anyway it's a question about whether
that age of חינוך chinuch is defined case-by-case or some objective standard.
Here's a קטן katan that's good enough to read the מגילה, Megillah,
but anyway somehow he's not at the age of חינוך. chinuch. So
since if he's not at the age of חינוך chinuch there's not
even a Rabbinic מצוה mitzvah for him to do it, then he
certainly cannot fulfill the obligation. אבל קטן שהגיע לחינוך, Aval katan she'higia
l'chinuch, according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda once he's of the age
of חינוך, chinuch, אפילו לכתחילה כשר דברי רבי יהודה, afilu l'chatchila kasher
divrei Rabbi Yehuda, then he can do it. That's what רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda, said. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda מכשיר בקטן machshir b'katan because
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says a קטן katan is okay. So now
we're jumping through hoops to have this משנה מגילה Mishnah Megillah that
says a חרש chersh cannot do it to mean A, not deaf-mute
but only deaf, B, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and only saying that
you can't do it לכתחילה l'chatchila but בדיעבד b'dieved it's okay, and
the קטן, katan, there are two categories of קטן, katan, so רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda can be saying it, sometimes the קטן katan is
good, sometimes not good. A lot of hoops we're jumping through to
make it רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and to say that לכתחילה l'chatchila
it's not good. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, במה אוקמתא,
b'mai ukimta, so now what have you said this משנה Mishnah is
talking about? כרבי יהודה ובדיעבד אין לכתחילה לא. K'Rabbi Yehuda v'dieved in
l'chatchila lo. You're saying it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and you're trying
to say that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that בדיעבד b'dieved it's
okay but לכתחילה l'chatchila it's not good. והא דתניא, V'ha de'tanya, and
now we're going to repeat what we did last this morning, that
is it that trying to prove that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would
allow it even לכתחילה. l'chatchila. הא דתניא רבי יהודה בריה דרבי שמעון
בן פזי, Ha de'tanya Rabbi Yehuda brei d'Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi, that
which be taught of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the son of רבי
שמעון בן פזי, Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi, a different רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. המדבר ואינו שומע תורם לכתחילה, Ha'medaber v'eino shomeia torem l'chatchila, that
if somebody can speak and not hear you can take תרומה trumah
לכתחילה, l'chatchila, which means that we are not concerned that you are
not able to hear the ברכה bracha you are making. So here's
an opinion that says that there is no concern even לכתחילה l'chatchila
that you should hear what you're saying. So מאן היא, mani, who's
that going like? לא רבי יהודה ולא רבי יוסי, Lo Rabbi Yehuda
v'lo Rabbi Yosi, it's not going like either תנא tanna of our
משנה. Mishnah. אי רבי יהודה, Ee Rabbi Yehuda, בדיעבד אין לכתחילה לא,
b'dieved in l'chatchila lo, if it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda then you're
trying to say that the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of our משנה
Mishnah only allowed it בדיעבד, b'dieved, post facto, not לכתחילה. l'chatchila.
אי רבי יוסי, Ee Rabbi Yosi, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi certainly
isn't, בדיעבד נמי לא, b'dieved nami lo, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says
that even בדיעבד b'dieved it doesn't work. So basically the argument is
you're trying to say the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of our משנה
Mishnah would say לכתחילה l'chatchila you have to hear what you're saying.
But we know there's an opinion out there that says by the
תרומה trumah that you can make the ברכות brachas and you don't
have to hear what you're saying. So who is that opinion? It
must be רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it must be רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says it's לכתחילה l'chatchila okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא
מאי, ella mai, so fine, what do you want to say? רבי
יהודה ואפילו לכתחילה, Rabbi Yehuda va'afilu l'chatchila, you want to say it's
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of our
משנה Mishnah would say you could do it לכתחילה l'chatchila and he's
the one that says you can take the תרומה trumah לכתחילה. l'chatchila.
So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא הא דתניא, ella ha de'tanya, but I'm going
to prove to you the same way you proved to me that
there's an opinion out there that allows it to be done לכתחילה,
l'chatchila, I'm going to prove to you there's an opinion out there
that says you can't do it לכתחילה l'chatchila but you can do
it בדיעבד. b'dieved. הא דתניא, Ha de'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
braisa, לא יברך אדם ברכת המזון בלבו, lo yivarech adam birkat hamazon
b'libo,
don't do ברכת המזון birkat hamazon in your heart, don't do it
silently, ואם בירך יצא, v'im berach yatza, and if you did it
silently you're יוצא. yotzei. Now again that seems to be going even
further, that seems to be saying you didn't utter it at all,
you just thought it. But the גמרא Gemara here is interpreting this
to mean that you uttered it but you couldn't hear it. So
here's an opinion that says that even לכתחילה l'chatchila that לכתחילה l'chatchila
it's no good, בדיעבד b'dieved it's okay. So look, you tried to
prove to me that there's an opinion that לכתחילה's l'chatchila good, I'm
proving to you there's an opinion that לכתחילה's l'chatchila no good and
בדיעבד b'dieved it's okay. So who's that going to be like? מאן
היא, mani, who's that going like? לא רבי יהודה ולא רבי יוסי,
Lo Rabbi Yehuda v'lo Rabbi Yosi, according to you it's neither רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. אי רבי יהודה, Ee
Rabbi Yehuda, האמר אפילו לכתחילה נמי, hamar afilu l'chatchila nami, you're claiming
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says לכתחילה's l'chatchila okay.
ואי רבי יוסי, V'ee Rabbi Yosi, האמר אפילו בדיעבד נמי לא, hamar
afilu b'dieved nami lo, and if רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, he says
even בדיעבד b'dieved it's not good. So the גמרא Gemara says, so
now basically to summarize what we have, the question is does רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allow it even לכתחילה l'chatchila or only בדיעבד b'dieved
if you can't hear. And the problem is that we have both
of the opinions are represented in a ברייתא. braisa. One ברייתא braisa
says לכתחילה l'chatchila you can take תרומה trumah even if you can't
you're deaf and can't hear the ברכה, bracha, it's okay לכתחילה. l'chatchila.
And this other case by שמע shma says it's only okay בדיעבד.
b'dieved. So we have three opinions and two people. So how are
we going to make this work? You know normally you would say
by Jews that's not a problem, but here it's a problem. So
any one you pick for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the other one
is left orphan. So what are you going to do? So the
גמרא's Gemara answer, two answers, one is, the גמרא Gemara says. לעולם
רב יהודה היא *Le'olam Reb Yehuda hi*. It is רב יהודה *Reb
Yehuda*. ואפילו לכתחילה l'chatchila נמי *ve'afilu l'chatchila nami*, and רב יהודה *Reb
Yehuda* lets you do it לכתחילה l'chatchila, *l'chatchila*, like the משנה Mishna
*Mishnah* in תרומה *Terumah*. He would say it's okay לכתחילה l'chatchila *l'chatchila*.
What about the case of שמע Shema *Shma* that
says only בדיעבד be-di'avad *bedieved*? So, ואפילו לכתחילה נמי ולא קשיא הא
דידי הא דרביה *ve'afilu l'chatchila nami, v'lo kashya, hadidi, haderabbe*, that
actually the opinion that it's only good בדיעבד be-di'avad *bedieved*, that's רב
יהודה's *Reb Yehuda's* רבי *Rebbe* who says that. And how do you
know that? Because we have yet another ברייתא *Baraita* that shows that
this opinion that לכתחילה *l'chatchila* yes and לכתחילה *l'chatchila* no, בדיעבד bedieved
*bedieved* yes, is the opinion of the רבי *Rebbe* of רב יהודה
*Reb Yehuda*. דתניא *De-tanya*, we come in a ברייתא *Baraita*, אמר Amar
רב יהודה משום ר' אלעזר בן עזריה *amar Reb Yehuda mishum Reb
Elazar ben Azaryah*. רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda* said in the name of
ר' אלעזר בן עזריה *Reb Elazar ben Azaryah*, הקורא שמע Shema צריך
שישמיע לאזנו tzarich she-yashmia l'ozno *hakoreh shma tzarich she-yashmia l'ozno*. If you
say the שמע Shema, *Shma* you have to, you should really, what
צריך tzarich *tzarich* means, you should make it audible, שנאמר שמע ישראל
Shema Yisrael *shene'emar Shma Yisrael*. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands that
צריך *tzarich* means that you should, but בדיעבד bediavad *bedieved* it's okay.
So אמר לו ר' מאיר *amar lo Reb Meir*, so ר' מאיר
*Reb Meir* said back to him, ר' מאיר אומר שנאמר והיו הדברים
האלה אשר אנכי מצוך היום על לבבך al levavecha *Reb Meir omer
shene'emar vehayu hadevarim ha'eleh asher anochi metzavecha hayom al levavecha*, on your
heart, אחר כוונת הלב הן הן הדברים *achar kavanat halev hein hein
hadevarim*. It's enough that you thought it, or at least that you
uttered it; the main, the fundamental question is what you're thinking, not
what you're saying. Okay, and that's the center. So you don't have
to hear. So now what have we said? We said there are
two opinions about whether לכתחילה *l'chatchila* you have to hear what you're
saying, or is it
needed לכתחילה *l'chatchila* or not? And we're saying רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda*
would say you don't need it לכתחילה *l'chatchila*. The sources out there,
the texts out there that say you do need it לכתחילה *l'chatchila*,
that's רב יהודה's *Reb Yehuda's* רבי *Rebbe*, ר' אלעזר בן עזריה *Reb
Elazar ben Azaryah*, because we have a ברייתא *Baraita* that clearly says
that ר' אלעזר בן עזריה *Reb Elazar ben Azaryah* says you need
it לכתחילה *l'chatchila*, בדיעבד *bedieved* even if you didn't do it, it's
okay. So that's how we accommodate those two positions, רב יהודה *Reb
Yehuda* and רב יהודה's *Reb Yehuda's* רבי *Rebbe*. And now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, here's another answer. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, השתא
דאתית להכי *hashta de-atit l'hachi*, now that you've actually come to this
and introduced us this ברייתא *Baraita*, this ברייתא *Baraita*, in addition to
telling us ר' אלעזר בן עזריה *Reb Elazar ben Azaryah* says לכתחילה
*l'chatchila* yes, בדיעבד *bedieved* no, you've also shown us a position of
ר' מאיר *Reb Meir*. So השתא דאתית להכי אפילו תימא רב יהודה
כרביה סבירא ליה *hashta de-atit l'hachi, afilu teima Reb Yehuda ke-rabbei seira
lei*, maybe רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda* holds like his רבי *Rebbe*. רב
יהודה *Reb Yehuda* is of the opinion that you need it לכתחילה
*l'chatchila*, only בדיעבד *bedieved* it's okay. How about the opinion out there
that even לכתחילה *l'chatchila* was not a problem? That's ר' מאיר *Reb
Meir*. ולא קשיא הא רב יהודה הא ר' מאיר *v'lo kashya, ha
Reb Yehuda ha Reb Meir*. This is רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda*, this
is ר' מאיר *Reb Meir*. So that was essentially a complete repeat
of what we did this morning more or less, basically with the
upshot being what is רב יהודה's *Reb Yehuda's* position about being able
to hear? Do you need it לכתחילה *l'chatchila* or not? Both opinions
are represented in ברייתות *Baraitas* of different תנאים *Tannaim* and there's two
options. Either רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda* says you don't need it לכתחילה
*l'chatchila*, but his רבי *Rebbe*, ר' אלעזר בן עזריה *Reb Elazar ben
Azaryah* says you do,
or רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda* and his רבי *Rebbe* say you need
it לכתחילה *l'chatchila*, and ר' מאיר *Reb Meir* says you don't need
it לכתחילה *l'chatchila*. But we have all three opinions. You need it
לכתחילה *l'chatchila*, excuse me, you don't need it even לכתחילה *l'chatchila* to
be able to hear, you need it לכתחילה *l'chatchila* but not בדיעבד
*bedieved*, and ר' יוסי's *Reb Yossi's* opinion that even בדיעבד *bedieved* you
are not יוצא yotzei *yotze*. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here should
be noted assumes that there is no difference between what we're talking
about, between whether we're talking about שמע Shema *Shma*, or מגילה Megilla,
*Megillah*, or the ברכות *brachot* of תרומה *Terumah*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
here is leveling all of those. In a minute we'll see a
possibility to distinguish, but here it's assuming it's the same הלכה halacha
*halacha* across the board. Was there a question?
Hello? Yes.
Yes, ר' עקיבא *Reb Akiva* I hear specifically place. I thought ר'
עקיבא *Reb Akiva* was רב יהודה's *Reb Yehuda's* teacher.
Well, maybe that's a good point. He actually was. That's true.
That כרביה *ke-rabbei*, I don't have a full answer to that, but
כרביה *ke-rabbei* here just means the רבי *Rebbe* he's quoting in this
context, does not mean like his עיקר *ikkar* רבי *Rebbe*, but the
person who he said this tradition in the name of. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now that it
worked out all the possibilities of רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda*, let's see
where it goes. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay. אמר
רב חסדא אמר רב שילה הלכה halacha כרב יהודה שאמר משום ר'
אלעזר בן עזריה *Amar Rav Chisda amar Rav Shila, halacha ke-Reb Yehuda
she-amar mishum Reb Elazar ben Azaryah*. We rule like רב יהודה *Reb
Yehuda* in the name of ר' אלעזר בן עזריה *Reb Elazar ben
Azaryah*, that לכתחילה *l'chatchila* you need to hear what you're saying, but
not only that,
but where are we? And
we rule like רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda* of our משנה Mishna *Mishnah*
that makes it clear that you're יוצא בדיעבד yotzei be-di'avad. *yotze bedieved*.
So just so there should not be any confusion since it's not
clear exactly what רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda* said, he's saying we rule
you need it לכתחילה *l'chatchila* and we rule that בדיעבד *bedieved* you're
יוצא yotzei *yotze* even without it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
וצריכא *u-tzricha*, you need to tell me both of those. דאי אשמעינן
הלכה כרב יהודה *di-ashmian halacha ke-Reb Yehuda*, had you just said we
rule like רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda* of our משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*, הוה
אמינא hava amina אפילו לכתחילה *hava amina afilu l'chatchila*, I might have
thought that you don't even לכתחילה *l'chatchila* you don't have to be
able to hear. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan
*kamashma
lan*, הלכה כרב יהודה שאמר משום ר' אלעזר בן עזריה *halacha ke-Reb
Yehuda she-amar mishum Reb Elazar ben Azaryah*. No, we rule like what
רב יהודה *Reb Yehuda* said. So the
one minute. והיא אשמעינן להך רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda שאמר משום רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar. בן עזריה, if it had just said that we
like that position, that צריך שישמיע לאזנו you have to be able
to hear, הוה אמינא hava amina צריך ואין לו תקנה. tzarich ve-ein
lo takana. Even though צריך normally means that it's a לכתחילה requirement,
it's not absolutely clear and I might have thought that maybe even
בדיעבד you're not יוצא yotzei. if you didn't hear. So קא משמע
לן הלכה כרבי יהודה, halachah k'rabbi Yehuda, so it's saying we rule
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of our משנה to make it clear
that you're יוצא yotzei בדיעבד. So whatever the exact position of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is about לכתחילה, he is making it explicitly clear
that לכתחילה you need it but בדיעבד you're יוצא yotze. even without
it. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on and says the following:
אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef מחלוקת בקריאת שמע. machlokes bi-krias Shema.
It's all very nice that until now you've been assuming that ברכת
המזון birchas ha-mazon and ברכות של תרומה berachos shel terumah and all
that were exactly and מגילה, that it was all the same, but
I'm actually telling you it is not a universal debate. The debate
is only about קריאת שמע. krias Shema. אבל בשאר מצוות, Aval bi-shear
mitzvos, when it comes to everything else, דברי הכל divrei ha-kol לא
יצא. lo yatza. Everybody would say you're not יוצא. yotze. That's a
little bit of a surprise, דכתיב de-chsiv הסכת ושמע ישראל. hasket u-shma
Yisrael. Be ear and listen Israel. So he understands that the so
what does that mean? So it
means so he understands that the הסכת ושמע ישראל, hasket u-shma Yisrael,
right,
which is said universally, means that by all the other מצוות mitzvos
there really needs to be a הסכת, hasket, you really need to
be able to hear what you are saying, and it's only by
שמע Shema where we said על לבבך al levavecha. that there's a
possibility that the focus on כוונה kavana means that the need to
hear is not so central. So the whole debate is by שמע
Shema. but otherwise you always have to hear. So גמרא Gemara says
מיתיבי, meisivei, I'll ask you on this: לא יברך אדם ברכת המזון
בלבו ואם בירך יצא. lo yevarech adam birchas ha-mazon be-libo ve-im berach
yatza. We said that you are יוצא ברכת המזון birchas ha-mazon even
if you did not even if you said it, you know, without
hearing, maybe even if you only thought it. So you can't tell
me by all other מצוות mitzvos you absolutely must hear.
אלא Ella says the גמרא Gemara אי איתמר הכי איתמר. ei isamar
hachi isamar. Here's how it was said. אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav
Yosef מחלוקת בקריאת שמע. machlokes bi-krias Shema. The debate is only by
שמע, Shema דכתיב שמע ישראל. de-chsiv Shema Yisrael.
Since it says שמע Shema, ישראל there might be a requirement to
really be able to hear. אבל בשאר מצוות Aval bi-shear mitzvos דברי
הכל יצא. divrei ha-kol yatza.
By all other מצוות mitzvos you don't have to hear, you'll it's
enough to mutter, maybe it's not enough to think but it's enough
to mutter it, you do not have to hear it. והכתיב הסכת
ושמע ישראל? Ve-hachsiv hasket u-shma Yisrael? Doesn't it say listen and hear
Israel by other מצוות? mitzvos? Like a generic command which means you
have to hear what you're saying? So the גמרא says no, ההוא
בדברי תורה כתיב. hahu be-divrei Torah ksiv. That's just talking about listening
to תורה, Torah, learning תורה Torah and so on, it's not a
requirement about formally מצוות mitzvos that require speech. So this is a
fascinating גמרא about the idea of certain acts of speech. Whether an
act of speech in general requires that we be able to hear
what we're saying. Now we did understand defining an act of speech
as something audible. I think it's harder for us to understand why
if a person let's say is deaf, it's not an act of
speech if they can't hear it. I mean it's certainly true that
if you're not hearing what you're saying, you know, you're not relating
to it as much and, you know, but still to say that
it doesn't count as a general act of speech is a little
bit of a surprise, which is why, you know, the end conclusion
is very nice, that in general that is an act of speech
and the only question is by שמע Shema there might be a
heightened requirement to hear what you're saying and maybe as I said
this morning because maybe שמע Shema is basically something we are saying
primarily to ourselves and therefore we're making a declaration first and foremost
to ourselves. So in the end that's how we conclude that the
debate is only by שמע. Shema. I think the other opinion that
said שמע Shema had a lower standard went back to the other
idea of the focus of כוונה kavana by שמע, Shema, but in
the end we conclude that שמע Shema, might have a higher standard
and general speech does not require it being audible. Okay, so that's
a very important גמרא for all these other all these other מצוות
mitzvos and הלכות halachos that require speech. So now the גמרא continues
to the idea of the saying of שמע Shema, and saying it
precisely. קרא ולא דקדק באותיותיה. kara ve-lo dikdek be-osiyoseha. If you read
it and you were not precise in the letters. אמר רבי טבי
אמר רבי יאשיה amar Rabbi Tevi amar Rabbi Yoshiya הלכה כדברי שניהם
להקל. halachah k'divrei shneihem l'hakel. So in the משנה you remember they
split their vote, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said you don't have
to hear and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says you do have to
hear, and but so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was was more lenient,
and then when you're not being articulating it precisely, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda, says it's no good and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says it
is good. So the גמרא says in the end we rule leniently
both ways. if בדיעבד if you don't hear, it's okay, and B,
even if you do not articulate them well, even sharply the letters
and the words, you're also יוצא. And those two work nicely together
because again that points to the moving away from a highly formalistic
emphasis on the act of speech and reciting and allowing for the
weight and the pointing towards the כוונה kavana and the קבלת עול
מלכות שמים Kabbalat Ol Malchut Shamayim as being, you know, more central.
So therefore, even if you didn't hear and even if you weren't
so precise, you're still יוצא. Now the גמרא goes on: ואמר רבי
טבי אמר רבי יאשיה, V'amar Rabbi Tevi amar Rabbi Yoshiya, מאי דכתיב,
mai dechtiv, what's meant by the verse, שלוש הנה לא תשבענה, shalosh
heina lo tishbe'anah, three things will never be sated? שאול, Sheol, the
depths, you know, the underworld, ואוצר רחם, v'otzer rachem,
a barren womb, and then it doesn't quote the third one which
it says basically I think a land that is that's scorched that
needs water. Anyway, these things are desperately in need to be filled,
or are won't be sated. So the גמרא says, וכי מה עניין
שאול אצל רחם, v'chi mah inyan Sheol etzel rachem, what type of
a sort of juxtaposition is that, the underworld and the womb? אלא
לומר לך, ella lomar lach, to tell you, מה רחם מכניס ומוציא,
mah rachem machnis u'motzi, the same way the womb takes something in,
the semen, and then something comes out from it, the child, the
infant; אף שאול מכניס ומוציא, af Sheol machnis u'motzi, the underworld takes
into it, when you bury somebody they go in the world in
the ground, it's like they go into the שאול, Sheol, the depths,
and then they'll come out again, meaning תחיית המתים, techiyat hameisim, resurrection.
והלא דברים קל וחומר, vehala devarim kal vachomer, and it's a קל
וחומר: kal vachomer: ומה רחם שמכניסין בו בחשאי, u'mah rachem she'machnisin bo
b'chashai, by the womb, when what's put into it is done in
private, right, when the couple you know is having sex it's in
private; מוציאין ממנו בקולי קולות, motzi'in mimenu b'kolei kolot, and when the
infant comes out, it's like a big, you know, there's screaming, the
child is crying, there's a whole to-do, everybody is running to take
care of the woman, so it's very public. So if that's true,
שאול שמכניסין בו
בקולי קולות, Sheol she'machnisin bo b'kolei kolot, when you bury somebody and
that's also a very big event and a to-do and you know
it's very public, so there it's even, you know, if that's true
on the way in, אינו דין שמוציאין ממנו בקולי קולות, eino din
she'motzi'in mimenu b'kolei kolot, how much more so will it be a
tremendous event when the people come out of the graves and when
there's a תחיית המתים. techiyat hameisim. מכאן תשובה לאומרים אין תחיית המתים
מן התורה, mikan teshuvah l'omrim ein techiyat hameisim min HaTorah, and here
is a response to those who say that there's no basis for
the resurrection of the dead in the Torah. So that does not
seem to be the most persuasive argument; first of all, you didn't
even start with a פסוק pasuk about that's from the Torah, and
number two, you know, it's a very particular way of reading the
פסוק. pasuk. But anyway, he says in this to me is a
hint towards the idea of תחיית המתים. techiyat hameisim. Okay, that was
a total digression because it was the same person who said it.
So now we continue. תני רב אושעיא קמיה דרבא, Tani Reb Oshia
kamei d'Rava, רב אושעיא Reb Oshia taught in front of רבא: Rava:
וכתבתם, U'chtavtam, הכל בכתב, hakol bichtav, אפילו צוואות. afilu tzava'ot.
So now we're actually quite interestingly little digression of what has to
be written in the מזוזות. mezuzot. So it says וכתבתם על מזוזות
ביתך, U'chtavtam al mezuzot beitecha, you shall write them. So what do
you write? So we assume it means write the whole פרשה, parsha,
but actually, the logic would say write, you know, what I've just
said, maybe write until this פסוק, pasuk, but don't actually write the
פסוק pasuk that says וכתבתם. U'chtavtam. So that's what he's saying: no,
even וכתבתם U'chtavtam has to be written. הכל בכתב, Hakol bichtav,
you write it all in the מזוזה, mezuzah, אפילו צוואות, afilu tzava'ot,
even the command to write it, even the פסוק pasuk of וכתבתם.
U'chtavtam. So אפילו צוואות נמי. afilu tzava'ot nami. So the גמרא says,
אמר ליה דאמר לך מני, amar lei d'amar lach mani, so רבא
Rava said to
רב אושעיא, Reb Oshia, who told you this? רבי יהודה היא, Rabbi
Yehuda hi, it must be רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda. דאמר גבי סוטה,
d'amar gabei Sotah, who says by סוטה, Sotah, אלות כותב צוואות אינו
כותב. alot kotev tzava'ot eino kotev. So meaning רבא Rava says like
that's obvious, of course we write everything in the מזוזה. mezuzah. He
says the only reason you might have needed to tell me it
was you're dealing with the position of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda Because
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says when the Torah tells you to write
something else, write the פרשה parsha of
סוטה, Sotah, that's scraped into the water. So it says that the
כהן Kohen והכהן את האלות האלה, v'hakohen et ha'alot ha'eileh, he shall
write these curses. So what does he write? Does he just write
the curses, or does he also write the פסוק pasuk וכתב את
האלות האלה? v'chatav et ha'alot ha'eileh? So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
you just write the אלות, alot, you don't write the פסוק pasuk
that tells you to write the curses. So that's what he says:
גבי סוטה אלות כותב צוואות אינו כותב, gabei Sotah alot kotev tzava'ot
eino kotev, you write the אלות alot not the command. והתם הוא
דכתיב, vehatam hu dechtiv,
so there it's because the פסוק pasuk says וכתב את האלות האלה,
v'chatav et ha'alot ha'eileh,
write the אלות. alot. אבל הכא דכתיב וכתבתם, aval hacha dechtiv u'chtavtam,
here it doesn't limit it the אלות, alot, it just says write
them very generally, אפילו צוואות נמי, afilu tzava'ot nami, even the command
as well. and the word even the words that tell you to
write need to be written even the command needs to be written.
So Rava said yes of course you write the whole thing but
it's making a good point that even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who
says by סוטה Sottah you don't write the whole thing here he
would agree because the verse is more general. So the Gemara says
אטו טעמא דרבי יהודה משום דכתיב וכתב? Atu ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda mishum
de-chtiv ve-chasav? So then the Gemara understood that the difference was he
wanted to say וכתב ve-chasav write and here it says וכתבתם u-chesavtam
write them which means all of them. So the Gemara says רבי
יהודה is not just because it says וכתב ve-chasav you know sort
of simply. טעמא דרבי יהודה משום דכתיב אלות. Ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda mishum
de-chtiv alot.
It's because the תורה Torah is explicit what you write. It says
write the curses אלות אין ציווי לא alot in tzivui lo only
write the curses not the command. So here where it didn't say
write X it just said write so you know that's generic enough
and therefore it would include everything. So the point is you don't
need a דרשה drasha of וכתבתם. u-chesavtam. All you need to say
is it doesn't say אלות alot it's not specific and if it's
not specific it includes everything. So the Gemara says no אצטריך itztrich
you still need to have a דרשה drasha by this פרשה parsha
by מזוזה Mezuzah to tell you everything is included. Why do you
need a דרשה? drasha? סלקא דעתך אמינא Salca daitach amina I would
have thought to say נילף כתיבה כתיבה מהתם neilaf ktiva ktiva me-hasam
let's apply the rule of סוטה Sottah to the מזוזה. Mezuzah. מה
התם אלות אין ציווי לא Mah hasam alot in tzivui lo the
same way there you only write what precedes it you don't write
the command to write it הכא נמי ציווי לא hacha nami tzivui
lo here too you write what precedes it and not the command.
So if I didn't have a special דרשה drasha I would have
said I use סוטה Sottah as my model. Therefore כתב רחמנא וכתבתם
ktav rachmana u-chesavtam there it says write them so the them is
to be all inclusive אפילו ציווי afilu tzivui
write it all even write the פסוק pasuk that tells you to
write it. Okay so that's a fascinating little discussion that there was
even a הוה אמינא that the מזוזה Mezuzah would not include the
entire פרשה parsha it would end before the פסוק pasuk of וכתבתם.
u-chesavtam. But anyway partly the reason that we're bringing it in now
is because now we're going to do another דרשה drasha based on
I mean well like more working not based on וכתבתם u-chesavtam but
we're working through the פסוק pasuk and let's take a look at
what the next stage is. So the Gemara says like this תני
רבי עובדיה קמיה דרבא. Tani Rabbi Ovadia kamei de-Rava.
So that was what רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshia taught רבא Rava based
on the וכתבתם u-chesavtam פסוק. pasuk. Now רבי עובדיה Rabbi Ovadia is
teaching רבא Rava based on the other word in the פרשה parsha
ולמדתם ve-limadetem teach them. And what does he tell him? And this
is where it ties into our theme שיהא לימודכם תם She-yehei limudchem
tam
your learning or your teaching should be complete. Now what does that
mean? שייתן ריוח בין הדבקים. She-yiten revach bein ha-dveikim. You should give
a little space between the things that are stuck together. Now sometimes
that's used in general about תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and a little
metaphorically which means you know don't rush onto the next topic give
a little space give a breather give time to reflect to internalize
before you move onto the next topic. Not exactly a policy of
the דף יומי. Daf Yomi. Anyway but here we're going to also
translate it more concretely in terms of the מצוה mitzvah of reciting
שמע. shema, So let's take a look. So it says עני רבא
בתריה Ani Rava basrei so then רבא Rava sort of responded to
this the same way before it was a דרשה drasha of וכתבתם
u-chesavtam and רבא Rava responded back so here it's a דרשה drasha
of ולמדתם ve-limadetem and רבא Rava responds back and what does he
say? כגון Kegon here's what I think it means says רבא Rava
על לבבך. al levavecha
It's talking about the reciting of שמע we discussed reciting it in
a precise way בדיעבד even if it's not precise but it should
be precise. So one of the ways you make it precise is
you don't let one word run into the next. So if one
word ends with the same letter that the next word begins with
you could you know if you're sloppy you'll turn it into one
word על al לבבך levavecha. you know it's like one big word.
No על al space לבבך. levavecha That's ריוח בין הדבקים revach bein
ha-dveikim a space between things that would be stuck together. על space
לבבכם levavchem בכל be-chol space לבבך בכל be-chol space לבבכם. levavchem. Okay
so it doesn't become בכל לבבכם be-chol levavchem you know one big
word. Now the next few are the next one is interesting
עשב בשדך eisev be-sadecha
grass in your field. Now that's a ב bet and a ב
bet so exactly how you would have run one into the other
but maybe you would have been so sloppy you would have said
עשב בשדך eisev be-sadecha or something I don't know but there anyway
it's harder to see the point.
ואבדתם מהרה ve-avadtem mehera
הכנף פתיל ha-kanaf pasil there also it's a פ pei פ pei
so it seems to be focusing on the letter and a little
less you know and a little less on exactly how it's being
articulated but presumably maybe you would have been sloppy to have made
that the same. אתכם מארץ. eschem me-aretz. Okay so those are all
the things be careful when you read it to give a space
to separate the word. Now and then the Gemara ends this point
with a little מוסר mussar or a little like you know encouragement.
אמר רבי חמא רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Chama Rabbi Chanina so כל
הקורא קריאת שמע ומדקדק באותיותיה kol ha-korei Krias Shema u-medakdek be-osiyoseha anybody
says שמיעה *Shmiah*, קריאת שמע *Krias shema* and is careful with the
letters, מצננים לו גיהנום *Metzaninim lo gehennom*, they sort of cool down
גיהנום *Gehennom* for you, שנאמר בפרש שדי מלכים בה תשלג בצלמון *Shene'emar
Bifros Shad-dai melachim bah tashleg be-Tzalmon*. So when God sort of spread
out the kings, like the, you know, like like when it was
frosted over in Salmon. So what does that mean? אל תקרי בפרש
*Al tikrei Bifros*, when God sort of spread out, אלא בפרש *ela
Befareish*, if you say, are if you articulate the words correctly. אל
תקרי בצלמון *Al tikrei be-Tzalmon*, don't say in Salmon which is a
place, אלא בצלמות *ela be-Tzalmoves*, in the place of death in גיהנום
*Gehennom*. So if you are בפרש *Befareish*, if you say the words
explicitly,
then בפרש שדי *Befareish Shad-dai* meaning the words of God, you say
them explicitly, or עול מלכות שמים *ol malchus shamayim* רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says, so then מלכים *melachim*, so רש"י *Rashi* says מלכים *melachim* here
means the תורה Torah *Torah*, which is sort of like the crown
of the kings, so then that תורה *Torah* will תשלג בצלמון *tashleg
be-Tzalmon* will cool off גיהנום *Gehennom* for you. So it's quite fascinating.
I really don't know what to make with the metaphor. First here
you are, you're so careful saying שמע *Shema* precisely, but you're still
going to גיהנום *Gehennom*. It's just going to get cooled down for
you. And I really don't understand exactly the correspondence of being careful
with how you say שמע *Shema* with this whole image and metaphor.
So I don't know. But anyway, it's a nice encouragement to say
it carefully. Now תוספות *Tosafos* interestingly quotes the רי"ף *Rif*. It's actually
an interesting, it's one of the few תוספות *Tosafos*
that quote the רי"ף *Rif* about some other concerns. Now not everything
תוספות *Tosafos* says is in our רי"ף *Rif*, but let's look at
תוספות *Tosafos*.
So תוספות *Tosafos* says the following: בין הדבקים *bein hadaveikim*, רב אלפס
מוסיף כגון דחרה אף *Rav Alfas mosif kegon de-chara af*. So there
you see, it's the same sound but a different letter. But that,
you know, so you could say וחרף *ve-charaf*. ואם לא יתן רווח
אז נראה כמו וחרף *ve-im lo yitein revach az nireh kemo ve-charaf*,
which is like חרף *cheref*, like to, you know, to like blaspheme.
וכן מוסיף *ve-chein mosif*, and he also adds, וראיתם אותו *ure'isem oso*,
וזכרתם את *uzchartem es*, ועשיתם את *va'asisem es*. So there also, although
they're different letters, you know, you could just merge the words together,
שצריך ליתן רווח בין מ"ם שבסוף לאל"ף שבחילת תיבה שאחריה *she-tzarich litein
revach bein mem she-besof l'alef she-b'techilas teiva she-achareha*. Right? Because it's just,
you know, it's if if you're being sloppy, you will say it
like that: וראיתם אותו *ure'isem oso*, like, you know, it's like one
big word. וזכרתם את *uzchartem es*. So the מ"ם *mem* flows into
the sort of silent אל"ף *alef* at the beginning and it you
could become one word. וכן צריך להתיז זי"ן של תזכרו *ve-chein tzarich
le-atiz zayin shel tizkeru*, שלא ישמע שי"ן *shelo yishama shin* תשכרו *tishkeru*.
Right? That's, people are careful to make a very clear זי"ן *zayin*,
so it shouldn't say in order that you should תשכרו *tishkeru*, be
rewarded. שאילו שכר מצווה *she-eilu sechar mitzvah*, so we don't do them
in order to receive a reward. So a lot of this sort
of care we do in the reading of שמע *Shema* comes from
this גמרא *Gemara* and this further elaboration by the רי"ף *Rif* and
תוספות *Tosafos*. Okay, and now the גמרא *Gemara* continues and we'll hopefully
get to the משנה *Mishna* and that's to wrap this up the
following way. So it's actually we're going to have some more דרשות
*drashos* because our previous statement was רבי חמא ברבי חנינא *Rabbi Chama
bar Rabbi Chanina*. So actually no, wait. רבי חמא ברבי חנינא *Rabbi
Chama bar Rabbi Chanina* was where was he? He was two back
I think.
He was somewhere here.
Oh yeah, yeah, two lines ago. אמר רבי חמא ברבי חנינא *Amar
Rabbi Chama bar Rabbi Chanina* was the one about גיהנום *Gehennom* cooling
off for you. So now that we're talking about him, we'll get
some other things he said. ואמר רבי חמא ברבי חנינא *Ve'amar Rabbi
Chama bar Rabbi Chanina*, למה נסמכו אהלים לנחלים *lama nismchu ohalim lenachalim*?
דף ט"ו עמוד א' *daf tes-vav amud aleph*. Why were the tents
juxtaposed to rivers? Where were tents juxtaposed to rivers? דכתיב *De-chsiv* by
בלק *Balak*, כנחלים נטיו כגנת עלי נהר *kenachalim nitayu kegannos alei nahar*,
like the rivers that have been stretched for us, like the like
the gardens by the river, כאהלים נטע ה' *ke'ohalim
nata Hashem*, like the אהלים *ohalim* which God has planted. Now רש"י
*Rashi* says that's the אהל *ohel*, tents, because נטע *nata* you could
that's is a verb that is used by plant tents, to pitch
a tent. תוספות *Tosafos* says no, כאהלים *ke'ohalim* there means אהל *ohel*
which is a type of a of a tree, you know,
more of אהלות *ahalos*. So תוספות *Tosafos* says the אהל *ohel* that
we're talking about is that the the פסוק *pasuk* right next to
this is מה טבו אהליך יעקב *mah tovu ohalecha Yaakov*. Okay, but
either way we have אהל *ohel* as the tent juxtaposed to rivers
and tent of course here symbolizing the tent of תורה *Torah*. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says what's the point of this juxtaposition? לומר לך
*Lomar lach*, to tell you, מה נחלים מעלים את האדם מטומאה לטהרה
*mah nechalim ma'alim es ha'adam mi-tum'ah le-taharah*, the same way rivers can
be a מקווה *mikvah* and can make you come rise up from
טומאה *tum'ah* to טהרה *taharah*, אף אהלים *af ohalim* תורה *Torah* does
the same thing, מעלים את האדם מכף חובה לכף זכות *maalim es
ha'adam mi-kaf chovah le-kaf zechus*, rises you up from the from being
on the sort of guilty side of the scale to the merit
side of the scale. Now there is here a theme of both
of these statements, right, being careful in the saying of the words
of the שמע *Shema* which also is very connected to תלמוד תורה
*Talmud Torah*, cools off גיהנום *Gehennom*, learning תורה *Torah*. raises you up
from a judgment of גיהנום and raises you up to being deserving
of reward. Okay, so now the גמרא finishes this with the last
point in the משנה, which is reading out of order. Let's take
a look. הקורא למפרע, Hakoreh l'mafrea, if you read out of order
לא יצא. lo yatza. רבי אמי ורבי אסי הוו קטרי ליה גננא
לרבי אלעזר. Rabbi Ami v'Rabbi Assi havu katrei lei ganana l'Rabbi Elazar.
So Rabbi Ami and Rabbi Assi were basically knotting
a an awning, רש"י says it's a חופה chuppah for רבי אלעזר.
Rabbi Elazar רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar was going to get married and
they were there, they were stitching his חופה chuppah for him, very
beautiful. So like that's, you know, a good a good precedent for
the whole idea of like these handmade חופות chuppot and so on.
So they were doing it, they were making a חופה chuppah for
him. Now אמר להו, amar lehu, so there he was, he was
the חתן, chassan, he wasn't supposed to be working, they were doing
this for him. So he said to them אדהכי והכי איזיל ואשמע
מילתא בבי מדרשא. adeihachi v'hachi izil v'eshma milta b'bei midrasha. You know,
while you're doing that and I'm standing around here doing nothing, I
think I will catch a movie. No, I think I will go
to the בית מדרש Beis Medrash and hear what they're learning in
the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. ואייתי ואימא לכו, v'ayisei v'eima l'chu, and
you know what? I'll come back and I'll tell you. So we'll
all be able to learn תורה while you're in the middle of
making me this חופה. chuppah. אזיל, Azil, he went. אשכחיה לתנא דקתני
קמיה דרבי יוחנן. Ashkachei l'tanna d'katani kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan. There was a
תנא Tanna standing in front of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. And here's
what he taught in front of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
קרא וטעה, Kara v'ta'ah, you read and you made a mistake ואינו
יודע להיכן טעה, v'eino yodeia l'heichan ta'ah, you don't know where you
made your mistake. You know you slipped up, but you forget exactly
where you were, where you're holding. So the הלכה is you have
to say it in order. If you have to say it in
order, so what you do if you don't know where you were
and where you made the mistake is you have to go back
to the earliest point that you know you got right and do
it again from there. So here's what he says.
באמצע הפרק, B'emtza haperek, let's say you're between sections of the שמע,
between the first and the second or second and third, and you
don't remember which is coming next. Wait a minute, am I up
to the second פרק perek or am I up to the third
פרק? perek? You don't remember which פרק perek you're up to. So
what do you do? יחזור לראש. Yachzor l'rosh. You go back to
the beginning—beginning not the beginning of שמע, but to the first break.
If you don't know which פרק perek you're between, you'd better go
back to the beginning of the second פרק. perek. בין פרק לפרק.
Bein perek l'perek. I'm sorry, I jumped ahead, excuse me. I was
already saying the next thing. טעה באמצע הפרק, Ta'ah b'emtza haperek, excuse
me. If you made a mistake in the middle of a פרק,
perek, you know which פרק perek you're in. I know I'm in
שמע, I know I'm in והיה אם שמוע. V'haya im shamoa. I
made a mistake somewhere here and I don't know where I made
it. So you don't know where you made the mistake in that
פרק, perek, you יחזור לראש, yachzor l'rosh, you go to the beginning
of that פרק perek that you know that you're in. בין פרק
לפרק, Bein perek l'perek, one second, if you—if your mistake is between
the chapters, you don't know—you're between a chapter and you don't know
which chapter is coming next. Are you between one and two or
two and three? Then יחזור לפרק ראשון, yachzor l'perek rishon, go back
to the first chapter, meaning to between one and two. Okay? So
if you don't know where you are in a section, go to
the beginning of the section. If you don't know which section you're
up to, then go to the first section, or go to the
first break if you know you're in a break.
Then he goes on and says בין כתיבה לכתיבה יחזור לכתיבה ראשונה.
bein kesivah l'kesivah yachzor l'kesivah rishonah. Right? This I think happens frequently.
When you say וכתבתם, u'chsavtem, right, you've got וכתבתם u'chsavtem in both
places. So you can sort of slip from one וכתבתם u'chsavtem to
the other וכתבתם. u'chsavtem. So you know you're messed up in וכתבתם
u'chsavtem and you forgot—oh my gosh, wait, which וכתבתם u'chsavtem am I
in? Am I in the first וכתבתם u'chsavtem or the second? So
since you don't know, you gotta go back to the first one.
Okay. אמר
so that—what—that's what he said. All of that was pretty, you know,
relatively self-evident. Okay, you do go back to the place where you
know you're good. But now let's see what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
responds. אמר ליה רבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan responded, לא שנו אלא שלא פתח בלמען ירבו ימיכם. lo shanu
ela shelo pasach b'lmaan yirbu yomeichem. All of this that you don't
know where you made your mistake or whatever is if you didn't
start yet למען ירבו ימיכם. l'maan yirbu yomeichem. אבל פתח בלמען ירבו
ימיכם, aval pasach b'lmaan yirbu yomeichem, if you started with למען ירבו
ימיכם, l'maan yirbu yomeichem, סירכיה נקט ואזיל, sirchei nakat v'azil, then you'll
just go by habit. Meaning, right, the פרשיות parshiyot stop being so
similar starting in the פסוק למען ירבו ימיכם. pasuk l'maan yirbu yomeichem.
So he says once you hit למען ירבו ימיכם, l'maan yirbu yomeichem,
then you can assume
that that you did not make a mistake in that section. So
let's say, for example, you're somewhere in the middle of אמת ויציב
Emes V'yatziv and then you sort of like got lost—and then you
forgot—oh wait a minute, I made a mistake somewhere, I'm not sure
where I made a mistake. As long as you know you started
למען ירבו ימיכם l'maan yirbu yomeichem correctly, you can assume that from
that point till אמת Emes you did it correctly because that just
flows and that everybody knows by habit. So you can assume that
there wasn't a mistake in that section. So—so that's a very interesting
assumption about human nature. Anyway, so אתא ואמר להו, ata v'amar lehu,
so רבי אלעזר came back and told רבי אמי ורבי אסי Rabbi
Ami v'Rabbi Assi what he just heard in the name of רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, אילו
לא באנו אלא לשמוע דבר זה דיינו, ilu lo banu ela lishmoa
davar zeh dayeinu, had we only—had we not come even just to
hear this one thing, it would have been enough. You know, we
were here making your whole חופה, chuppah, but the whole trip would
have been worth it just to hear this wonderful teaching that once
you hit למען ירבו ימיכם, l'maan yirbu yomeichem, you can assume you
get till the end of אמת, emes, you got it correct. Now
this idea by the way I should say is not just important
for this הלכה of שמע, but the principle of סירכיה נקט sirchei
nakat that we assume people fall into habits, and if they can't
remember exactly what they did for certain halachic purposes, we can assume
they did what they always do, is an important principle, and sometimes
there's questions about like, I don't remember if I salted the meat
before I put it into the pot, you know, certain types of
things where we can actually make assumptions based on behavior that is
very habitual and assume that you just did what is your habit.
There is some question how far you can take it, but it's
a very important halachic principle. So, unless there's any or a question
there before?
No?
Okay, so we are going to end here. So we are ברוך
השם baruch Hashem caught up, and I will see you all tomorrow
bright and early. לילה טוב. laila tov.